<?xml version="1.0"?>
<ead xmlns:ns2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9 http://www.loc.gov/ead/ead.xsd">
  <eadheader audience="internal" countryencoding="iso3166-1"
  dateencoding="iso8601" langencoding="iso639-2b"
  repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid countrycode="us" mainagencycode="npkmc">
    npkmc_5210</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>E. T. Sweet Letter Regarding Smallpox to
        Margaretta Titus Finding Aid</titleproper>
        <author>Dulcie Beauregard</author>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <date>2023-05-31</date>
        <publisher>Marist College Archives and Special
        Collections</publisher>
        <address>
          <addressline>3399 North Road</addressline>
          <addressline>Poughkeepsie, NY</addressline>
          <addressline>Poughkeepsie</addressline>
          <addressline>New York</addressline>
          <addressline>12601</addressline>
          <addressline>United States</addressline>
        </address>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Abigail Bowen</creation>
      <langusage>
        <language langcode="eng">English</language>
      </langusage>
      <descrules>Describing Archives: a Content
      Standard</descrules>
    </profiledesc>
  </eadheader>
  <archdesc level="Collection">
    <did>
      <unittitle label="Title">E. T. Sweet Letter Regarding
      Smallpox to Margaretta Titus</unittitle>
      <unitid>npkmc-235-311</unitid>
      <origination>
        <persname source="local">Elizabeth Titus Sweet</persname>
      </origination>
      <physdesc>
        <extent>2 Folders</extent>
      </physdesc>
      <langmaterial>
        <language langcode="eng">English</language>
      </langmaterial>
      <abstract>This collection consists of a single letter written
      by Elizabeth Titus Sweet of Dutchess County, New York on
      March 20th and March 21st, 1864, regarding Maggie Sweet’s
      diagnosis of smallpox. This letter is addressed to Elizabeth
      Titus Sweet’s brother Stephen Titus and sister-in-law
      Margaretta Titus living in Meigs County, Ohio.</abstract>
      <unitdate type="inclusive">March 20th, 1864 – March 22nd,
      1864</unitdate>
      <unitdate type="bulk">March 20th, 1864 – March 22nd,
      1864</unitdate>
      <repository>
        <corpname>Marist College Archives and Special
        Collections</corpname>
        <address>
          <addressline>3399 North Road</addressline>
          <addressline>Poughkeepsie, NY</addressline>
          <addressline>Poughkeepsie</addressline>
          <addressline>New York</addressline>
          <addressline>12601</addressline>
          <addressline>United States</addressline>
        </address>
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
        ns2:type="simple"
        ns2:href="https://archives.marist.edu/" />
      </repository>
    </did>
    <accessrestrict>
      <p>There are no restrictions on this collection</p>
    </accessrestrict>
    <userestrict>
      <p>Individuals requesting reproductions expressly assume the
      responsibility for compliance with all pertinent provisions
      of the Copyright Act, 17 U.S.C. ss101 et seq. Patrons further
      agree to indemnify and hold harmless the Marist College
      Archives &amp; Special Collections and its staff in
      connection with any disputes arising from the Copyright Act,
      over the reproduction of material at the request of patrons.
      For more information please visit the following website:
      https://www.loc.gov/copyright/title17/.</p>
    </userestrict>
    <bioghist>
      <p>In the late eighteenth century, John Titus moved to
      Dutchess County from Long Island, New York. By 1780, he
      established his family’s first woolen mill in Washington
      Hollow in the Town of Pleasant Valley. Titus also bought
      1,600 acres of land in Southeast Ohio, where several of his
      sons, Stephen and Nicholas, would later move to operate
      farms. Sheep were raised for their wool in Ohio which was
      then sent back to Dutchess County and the Titus Woolen Mill.
      In 1828, Elias Titus (another son of John Titus) partnered
      with his brother-in-law Silas Sweet to purchase a grist mill
      and open land that would turn into the grounds for this new
      woolen mill. This mill was established along the Wappinger
      Creek, and the hamlet of “Titusville” as we know it was then
      named in Elias Titus’ honor.</p>
      <p>At the peak of Titus Woolen Mill’s production, there were
      over one hundred employees. Broadcloth was the primary
      material in production. In the Civil War Era, the Titusville
      mill would manufacture material for blankets and other
      products for the Union Army. By the 1880s, the Titus Woolen
      Mill became associated with the Gifford, Sherman, and Innis
      Company of Poughkeepsie. However, the Titus Woolen Mill was
      forced to cease operations in the 1890s after a lightning
      strike destroyed the mill.</p>
      <p>Stephen Titus (1796-1871), son of John Titus, was born in
      Washington, Dutchess County, New York, but moved to Meigs
      County, Ohio in 1833, where his father held property. In
      1836, Titus wed Margaretta Lois Nye, a native of Meigs
      County, Ohio. Titus would go on to represent the Ohio county
      he called home in the 1840-1841 legislature and was also
      president of the Meigs County Agricultural Society for a
      time. Stephen Titus passed at the age of seventy-five at his
      home in Rutland, Ohio on September 13th, 1871, while
      Margaretta died on October 31st, 1907, at the age of
      ninety-two. Together, Stephen and Margaretta Titus had four
      children, Samuel, Phebe, Margaret, and George. George Titus
      became a prominent farmer, while Samuel fought in the Civil
      War and lost an arm. Phebe Titus went on to marry New York
      politician Stephen Taber.</p>
      <p>Elizabeth Titus Sweet was the daughter of John Titus and
      sister of Ohio farmer Stephen Titus, making her sister-in-law
      Margaretta Nye Titus. Elizabeth Titus Sweet lived in a home
      with husband Silas Sweet on Titus Woolen Mill property near
      brother Elias Titus. In 1864, Elizabeth Titus Sweet wrote to
      her brother Stephen and sister-in-law Margaretta regarding
      Elizabeth’s assumed daughter Maggie’s case of smallpox.</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent>
      <p>This is a letter written by Elizabeth Titus Sweet of
      Dutchess County, New York on March 20th and March 21st, 1864,
      regarding Maggie Sweet’s diagnosis of smallpox. This letter
      is addressed to Elizabeth Titus Sweet’s brother Stephen Titus
      and sister-in-law Margaretta Titus living in Meigs County,
      Ohio.</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <controlaccess xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
      <subject authfilenumber="sh85123612" source="lcsh"
      ns2:type="locator"
      ns2:href="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85123612">
      Smallpox</subject>
    </controlaccess>
    <dao xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
    ns2:type="simple" ns2:href="" ns2:title="" />
    <prefercite>
      <p>[Description of item, date, location of item in order of
      box number, folder number], in the E. T. Sweet Letter
      Regarding Smallpox to Margaretta Titus, Archives and Special
      Collections, James A. Cannavino Library, Marist College</p>
    </prefercite>
    <processinfo>
      <p>Processed by: Dulcie Beauregard, May 2023</p>
    </processinfo>
    <arrangement>
      <p>This collection is organized chronologically, with the
      dated letter placed before the dated envelope.</p>
    </arrangement>
    <acqinfo>
      <p>Collection was purchased for the Marist College Archives
      &amp; Special Collections</p>
    </acqinfo>
    <accruals>
      <p>No accruals are expected.</p>
    </accruals>
    <dsc>
      <c id="c-2-1" level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle>E. T. Sweet Letter Regarding Smallpox to
          Margaretta Titus</unittitle>
          <unitdate type="inclusive"
          normal="1864-03-20/1864-03-22">
          1864-03-20-1864-03-22</unitdate>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>This collection contains a singular letter and
          envelope.</p>
        </scopecontent>
        <c id="c-3-2" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter</unittitle>
            <unitdate type="inclusive"
            normal="1864-03-20/1864-03-21">
            1864-03-20-1864-03-21</unitdate>
            <container type="Box">1</container>
            <container type="Folder">1</container>
            <dao xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
            ns2:type="simple"
            ns2:href="https://maristarchives.catalogaccess.com/archives/101214"
            ns2:title="View the letter online here" />
          </did>
        </c>
        <c id="c-4-2" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Envelope</unittitle>
            <unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1864-03-22">
            1864-03-22</unitdate>
            <container type="Box">1</container>
            <container type="Folder">2</container>
          </did>
        </c>
      </c>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
