<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--https://www.loc.gov/ead/ead.xsd-->
<ead xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:ns2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xsi:schemaLocation="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9 https://www.loc.gov/ead/ead.xsd">
  <!--Header portion of EAD -->
  <eadheader langencoding="iso639-2b" scriptencoding="iso15924" repositoryencoding="iso15511" countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601">
    <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-NPkMC" url="http://www.marist.edu">npkmc_224_143</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>Hudson River Environmental Society Library</titleproper>
        <author>Processed by: John Ansley, PhD, 2008, Finding Aid Encoded by: Monish M. Singh, 2008;
          Finding Aid Encoding updated by: Abigail Bowen, 2022</author>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Marist College <lb/>Archives and Special Collections </publisher>
        <address>
          <addressline>3399 North Road <lb/>Poughkeepsie, NY 12601 <lb/>Phone: 845-575-5217
            <lb/>Fax: 845-575-3150 <lb/>Email: library.archives@marist.edu<lb/>Website:
            https://archives.marist.edu/</addressline>
        </address>
        <date type="publication" normal="2008-07-28">2008-07-28</date>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Monish M. Sing <date normal="2008">2008</date>
      </creation>
      <langusage>Finding aid written in <language langcode="eng" scriptcode="Latn">English</language></langusage>
      <descrules><abbr>DACS</abbr>Describing Archives: A Content Standard. Chicago: Society of
        American Archivists, 2013.</descrules>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <list>
        <item>April 2022, EAD updated by Abigail Bowen</item>
      </list>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <!--Description portion of EAD-->
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary</head>
      <unittitle label="title">Hudson River Environmental Society Library</unittitle>
      <unitdate type="inclusive" normal="2000">1965 - 2001</unitdate>
      <origination label="creator">
        <corpname>The Hudson River Environmental Society (HRES)</corpname>
      </origination>
      <unitid countrycode="US" repositorycode="US-NpkMC">NPKMC-224-143</unitid>
      <physdesc>
        <extent>12 Linear Feet</extent>
        <extent>1226 Monographs</extent>
      </physdesc>
      <langmaterial>
        <language>English</language>
      </langmaterial>
      <repository>
        <corpname>Marist College <lb/>Archives and Special Collections </corpname>
      </repository>
      <abstract>The Hudson River Environmental Society (HRES) was founded in 1970 to foster research
        on the Hudson River environment and related coastal areas, provide a forum for communication
        and cooperation among researchers, and make the results of environmental research available
        and accessible to concerned citizens and public officials. The Hudson River Environmental
        Society Library contains approximately 12 linear feet of records and 1,226 monographs. The
        records consist of field notes, meetings minutes, research papers, memorandum, and newspaper
        and article clippings. The monographs consist of scientific reports generated by government
        agencies and private organizations concerned with the environmental condition of the Hudson
        River. </abstract>
      <physloc>Please contact the Marist College Archives and Special Collections for information
        regarding use and access of this collection.</physloc>
    </did>
    <acqinfo>
      <head>Acquisitions Information</head>
      <p>The Hudson River Environmental Society donated their library to the Marist College Archives
        and Special Collections. </p>
    </acqinfo>
    <accessrestrict>
      <head>Restrictions to Access</head>
      <p>There are no restrictions on this collection</p>
    </accessrestrict>
    <userestrict>
      <head>Notice of Copyright</head>
      <p>Individuals requesting reproductions expressly assume the responsibility for compliance
        with all pertinent provisions of the Copyright Act, 17 U.S.C. ss101 et seq. Patrons further
        agree to indemnify and hold harmless the Marist College Archives and Special Collections and
        its staff in connection with any disputes arising from the Copyright Act, over the
        reproduction of material at the request of patrons. For more information please visit the
        following website: http://www.loc.gov/copyright/title17/.</p>
    </userestrict>
    <bioghist>
      <head>Historical Note</head>
      <p>The Hudson River Environmental Society (HRES), a nonprofit membership organization, was founded in 1970 to foster research on the Hudson River environment and related coastal areas, provide a forum for communication and cooperation among researchers, and make the results of environmental research available and accessible to concerned citizens and public officials. </p>
      <p>HRES works to facilitate and coordinate research in the physical, biological and social sciences; environmental engineering; resource management; urban and regional planning; and other disciplines in the Hudson River region. Equally important, HRES serves as a channel of communication between the research community and researchers. HRES strives to ensure that the best possible information is available to those who potentially affect the environment. The Society's membership includes corporate members, individuals from major academic and research institutions, consulting firms, government agencies industries and conservation organizations concerned with environmental matters in the Hudson Valley region and interested citizens. The best known activities of HRES are its conferences and workshops on subjects of current environmental interest. HRES has organized topical meetings on such subjects as: PCBS, acid rain, dredging and soil disposal, the Hudson River fisheries, State Environmental Quality Review Act, freshwater and tidal wetlands, toxic and hazardous waste management, coal conversions, scenic and historic area preservation, energy and the future, and coastal revitalization and preservation. </p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent>
      <head>Collection Overview</head>
      <p>The Hudson River Environmental Society Library contains approximately 12 linear feet of records and 1,226 monographs. The records consist of field notes, meetings minutes, research papers, memorandum, and newspaper and article clippings. The monographs consist of scientific reports generated by government agencies and private organizations concerned with the environmental condition of the Hudson River. The monograph portion of the collection provides a comprehensive look at many issues that have arisen during the latter-half of the twentieth century. For instance, the collection contains materials generated by government agencies, non-profit organizations, and private companies (i.e. Consolidated Edison) concerning dredging the Hudson River to remove PCBs.</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <relatedmaterial>
      <p>
        <extref href="https://www.empireadc.org/search/catalog/npkmc_222_158">Grim Collection: Hudson River Fisheries Investigation, 1965 - 1968</extref>
      </p>
      <p>
        <extref href="https://www.empireadc.org/search/catalog/npkmc_222_095">Hudson River Conservation Society, Inc. Collection, 1930 - 1980</extref>
      </p>
      <p>
        <extref href="https://www.empireadc.org/search/catalog/npkmc_223_071">Hudson River Environmental Society Collection, 1963 - 2005</extref>
      </p>
      <p>
        <extref href="https://www.empireadc.org/search/catalog/npkmc_221_081">Hudson River Valley Greenway Council Collection, 1989 - 1996</extref>
      </p>
    </relatedmaterial>
    <dsc type="combined">
      <head>Deatiled Description of the Collection</head>
      <!--for a series with no subseries-->
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unitid>1</unitid>
          <unittitle>Hudson River Environmental Society Library</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>These materials may be searched on the James A. Cannavino online catalog. You
                  may browse the collection by entering "Hudson River Environmental Society" under a subject
                  search or you may search for a specific title or author by selecting the
                  Advanced Search option. To use this option most effectively you should
                  enter the "Hudson River Environmental Library" in the first search box and select
                  "Subject" for the search type. You may enter any additional terms or
                  keywords in the subsequent search boxes. This will allow you to search
                 the contents of this library. </p>
          <p>
            <extref href="https://library.marist.edu/">James A. Cannavino Library's on-line catalog</extref>
          </p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
